St. George L. Sioussat Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
St. George L. Sioussat Papers 1831-1959
MSS40188
Sioussat, St. George L. (St. George Leakin), 1878-1960
3,500 items
8 containers
3.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Historian, librarian, and archivist. Correspondence with American scholars and librarians concerning the location of Duff Green papers and transcripts and photostats of the correspondence of Green and others relating to American-British diplomacy, with emphasis on Green's missions to England. Also includes notes and memoranda from published and unpublished sources collected for the purpose of writing an account of Green's diplomatic career.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Cobden, Richard, 1804-1865--Correspondence.; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865--Correspondence.; Green, Duff, 1791-1875--Correspondence.; Green, Duff, 1791-1875.; Hume, Joseph, 1777-1855--Correspondence.; MacGregor, John, 1825-1892--Correspondence.; Peel, Robert, 1788-1850--Correspondence.; Sioussat, St. George L. (St. George Leakin), 1878-1960.; Tyler, John, 1790-1862--Correspondence.; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852--Correspondence.
Places
Great Britain--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--19th century.; United States--Foreign relations--Great Britain.
Occupations
Archivists.; Historians.; Librarians.
Acquisition Information
The papers of St. George L. Sioussat, historian, librarian, and archivist, were given to the Library of Congress by Sioussat and his wife, Julia Taber Sioussat (née Richardson), 1960-1961
Access and Restrictions
The papers of St. George L. Sioussat are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1878, Mar. 13 Born, Baltimore, Md.
1896 Graduated, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md.
1899 1904 Assistant instructor in history, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.
1904 1911 Professor of history and economics, University of the South, Sewanee, Tenn.; dean of arts and sciences, 1909-1911
1911 1917 Professor of history, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tenn.
1917 1920 Littlefield Professor of American history, Brown University, Providence, R.I.
1920 1938 Professor of American history, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa.
1934 1942 Chairman, committee on the library, American Philosophical Society
1938 1948 Chief, Manuscript Division, Library of Congress, and incumbent of Library's Chair of American History
1938 1948 Member, National Historical Publications Commission.
1947 1950 Vice president, American Philosophical Society
1948 1960 Honorary consultant in American historiography, Library of Congress
1960, Aug. 31 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of St. George Leakin Sioussat (1878-1960) span the years 1831-1959 and consist of correspondence, 1926-1959, with American scholars and librarians concerning the location of Duff Green papers and transcripts and photostats of correspondence, 1841-1867, of Richard Cobden, Edward Everett, Duff Green, Joseph Hume, John MacGregor, Robert Peel, John Tyler, Daniel Webster, and others relating to American-British diplomacy, with emphasis on Green's missions to England. Also included are notes and memoranda from published and unpublished sources, including American, British, and French newspapers, pamphlets, and diplomatic dispatches collected for the purpose of writing an account of Green's diplomatic career.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is organized by topic or type of material.
Container List
- Correspondence regarding Duff Green Papers (Box 1)
  - 1926-1935, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1949-1959, undated (Box 1)
- Duff Green correspondence, 1841-1867, (4 folders) (Box 1)
- Lists and notes on Duff Green's correspondence, 1831-1844 (Box 1)
- Duff Green (Box 2)
  - Text and notes prepared by Sioussat, 1837-1843 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous bibliographical notes, bibliography, etc., undated (Box 2)
  - Notes for Dictionary of National Biography (Box 2)
- John Tyler, election, U.S. foreign policy, etc., 1841-1843 (Box 2)
- Sioussat's draft of introduction, Duff Green (Box 2)
- Abstract of Duff Green's "England and the United States" and introductory notes of Sioussat (Box 2)
- American politics and British foreign policy, 1840-1844 (Box 2)
- Principally notes on Green's correspondence, 1841-1843 (Box 2)
- Informal special agents of President John Tyler, introduction of special agents, 1841-1842 (Box 2)
- Duff Green, bibliography, British-American policies (Box 2)
- Texas, Monroe Doctrine, etc. (Box 2)
- Duff Green and Texas, photostats of letters and notes, 1844-1845 (Box 2)
- Notes, England and Texas, Duff Green and Ashbel Smith (Box 2)
- James K. Polk's administration, outline, Texas, etc., and Oregon (Box 2)
- Notes from Pilot, a Whig newspaper, 1840 (Box 3)
- Duff Green's letters to British and American newspapers, notes and text, 1841-1842, Jan. (Box 3)
- Duff Green's "England and the United States" with an introductory study of American opposition to the Quintuple Treaty, 1841 by Sioussat, part of text and galley, (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Foreign Office.O. 27: 414 and 415, slave trade; right of search; Quintuple Treaty, 1841 (Box 3)
- Notes, Journal des débats, Paris, France (Box 3)
- Le Moniteur (Box 3)
  - 1-IV-12-IV, 1842, Quintuple Treat, 1841, opinion (Box 3)
  - 5-II-13-III, 1842,Quintuple Treaty, 1841, opinion (Box 3)
  - 18-I-19-I, views of France, Quintuple Treaty, 1841 (Box 3)
  - 23- I, 1842,Quintuple Treaty, 1841, opinion (Box 3)
  - 25- I, 1842-29-I, Quintuple Treaty, 1841, opinion (Box 3)
- Chronicle (Box 3)
- Notes, London Times, Duff Green, 1842-1843 (Box 3)
- London Globe, 1843 (Box 3)
- The United States and England, by an American, Great Western Magazine, typed copy, 1942, Sept. (Box 3)
- Notes on Joseph Hume, Duff Green, Aberdeen correspondence, 1843 (Box 4)
- Lewis Cass letters, notes, 1841-1844 (Box 4)
- British-American trade relations, notes and bibliography, 1837-1842 (Box 4)
- Edward Everett work on ministers to England, outline, bibliography, and text of chapters 1 and 2, 1841 (Box 4)
- Duff Green on postal reform, text, notes, documents, copies of J. S. Jackson's "International Aspect of the Postal Service" (Box 4)
- Notes on English diplomatic correspondence, 1838-1841 (Box 4)
- Edward Everett's dispatches, notes on foreign policy of U.S. and Great Britain (Box 4)
- Notes of Sioussat, writing, review: Shortt, George Ernest, The Second Bank of the United States under Two Charters (Box 4)
- English-American politics, notes, 1840-1843 (Box 4)
- Notes on Duff Green, Everett, John Tyler correspondence, 1843 (Box 4)
- Edward Everett's dispatches, chiefly about slave trade, England and France, 1844-1846 (Box 4)
- Abstracts, Edward Everett's diary and letters, 1841 (Box 4)
- Green-Everett relations, notes, etc., 1841-1843 (Box 4)
- "Green's Activities in 1842," outline, notes, part of text, British mission, 1842-1843 (Box 5)
- Duff Green's second mission to England, personal business (Box 5)
- Notes relating to Green and his mission to England, 1840-1843 (Box 5)
- Duff Green, text, and European mission, 1843 (Box 5)
- Duff Green's second trip to Europe, text, 1842-1843 (Box 5)
- Notes and text on Duff Green's second trip to Europe, 1842-1843 (Box 5)
- Edward Everett-Daniel Webster missions to England, 1839-1843, (2 folders) (Box 5)
- Duff Green's English mission (Box 5)
- Duff Green in England, 1843 (Box 5)
- Notes, Duff Green in Paris, 1842- (Box 5)
- Duff Green's second mission to Europe, contributions to the Boston Post (Box 5)
- Duff Green business matter, notes U.S. Bank, etc., foreign finances, 1840-1843 (Box 6)
- Duff Green, U.S. loans, "Basis of Text," 1842 (Box 6)
- Green, views on finances, notes, 1839-1943 [1843] (Box 6)
- Duff Green, notes on George Peabody correspondence, 1841-1842 (Box 6)
- Notes from Baring Brothers papers, 1833-1842 (Box 6)
- Peel's financial reform, Aberdeen and Peel papers, Duff Green, 1841-1843 (Box 6)
- U.S. credit, John Tyler administration, 1841-1844 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous notes, Duff Green, John Tyler and others, 1840-1845 (Box 6)
- Philip Hone's diary, financial panics, 1837-1840 (Box 6)
- Arbitration miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Duff Green, miscellaneous notes from letters of American and British statesmen (Box 6)
- Duff Green notes and text, 1841- (Box 6)
- Notes, British-American relations (Box 6)
- Text, John C. Calhoun-Duff Green; Daniel Webster and Green to England, 1839; Green and the Whigs, 1840-1841; Green-Nicholas Biddle, 1837-1841 (Box 7)
- Duff Green, reform merchants, British policy, abolitionism, 1837-1843 (Box 7)
- Peel, Robert-Earl of Aberdeen Papers, U.S.-British commercial treaty, 1841,Oct.25-1842, Feb. 28 (Box 7)
- British trade, John C. Calhoun-Duff Green, etc., tariff, Corn Law, 1841-1843 (Box 7)
- British Corn Laws, free trade, Duff Green and J. Mac Gregor correspondence, etc., 1842 (Box 7)
- John C. Calhoun, notes from letters of various statesmen, 1840-1844 (Box 7)
- Notes, slave trade, Great Britain and France, 1840-1842 (Box 7)
- U.S.-British trade reciprocity, 1840-1843 1840-1843 (Box 7)
- Free labor policy in the British sugar colonies, notes, 1834-1860 (Box 7)
- Free labor in British colonies; also French slavery, notes and reports of W. J. Bell, D. Ditter, Rosaline Goldin and H. H. Sipes (Box 7)
- Report on the tariff, V. G. Setser, seminar report, 1842-1846 (Box 7)
- Prints and photocopies, England and the United States (Box 8)
- Illinois Central Railroad and Land Act of 1850, etc., 1850 (Box 8)
- Printed matter, (2 folders) (Box 8)
- Sioussat, St. George L. (Box 8)